<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Italy Today</title>
    <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today</link>
    <description>Daily briefing on Italian news</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <image>
      <url>https://briefings.my/italy-today/cover.png</url>
      <title>Italy Today</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today</link>
    </image>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 13:45:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <itunes:image href="https://briefings.my/italy-today/cover.png"/>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-15</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-15/2025-12-15-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**THE ROMAN OBSERVER**
Buongiorno, I am Amelia. It is Monday 15, and here is the view from Rome. Today's briefing was curated by DeepSeek-V3.2-Special.
**PART 1: THE HEADLINES (The &quot;Terza Pagina&quot;)**
1. **The Imam's Release: Government vs Judiciary**  
   - **The Fact:** A Turin court ordered the release of Tunisian imam Mohamed Shahin from a detention center, ruling his continued detention unlawful.  
   - **The Spin:** While left-leaning La Repubblica reported the decision with a focus on the legal reasoning, right-wing Il Giornale echoed Premier Meloni's outrage, accusing the judiciary of undermining national security.  
   - **The Takeaway:** The case underscores the escalating conflict between the executive and the judiciary over immigration policy, with both sides digging in.
2. **Budget Ballooning: 3.5 Billion for Businesses, Bridge Funds Delayed**  
   - **The Fact:** The government unveiled a last-minute package of €3.5 billion in the budget law, earmarked for business support, while postponing funding for the controversial Messina Bridge project.  
   - **The Spin:** Opposition parties and left-wing media slammed the move as proof of disarray, while Economy Minister Giorgetti argued it was necessary to boost a faltering economy.  
   - **The Takeaway:** The extra spending risks widening the deficit, but the real story is the quiet shelving of a flagship infrastructure promise.
3. **John Elkann Forced to Stand Trial Over Agnelli Inheritance**  
   - **The Fact:** A Milan judge ordered the forced indictment of Fiat chairman John Elkann on fraud charges related to the inheritance of Marella Caracciolo, widow of Gianni Agnelli.  
   - **The Spin:** Center-left outlets portrayed the decision as justice catching up with the elite; right-leaning commentators called it judicial overreach and pointed to Elkann's defense labeling the ruling &quot;abnormal.&quot;  
   - **The Takeaway:** The trial will shine an uncomfortable spotlight on Italy's most powerful industrial dynasty and could have ripple effects across the corporate landscape.
**PART 2: IL CAFFÈ (Rapid Fire)**  
- **Cannabis Sector Wins:** The Council of State ruled that companies can sell CBD oil, ending a two-year legal battle and giving a boost to Italy's hemp industry.  
- **IMF’s Mixed Report:** The IMF praised Italy's fiscal discipline but warned the government to &quot;keep pedaling&quot; to sustain growth and reduce public debt.  
- **Poll Shift:** A new poll shows a dip for Fratelli d'Italia and a rise for the Democratic Party, narrowing the gap.  
- **Ukraine Summit:** At the Berlin meeting, European leaders backed a multinational force for Ukraine and urged President Zelensky to consult his people on peace terms; Meloni said she expects &quot;progress.&quot;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-15</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-15/2025-12-15-audio.mp3" length="3148113" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>196</itunes:duration>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-16</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-16/2025-12-16-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**ITALY TODAY**
Welcome, I am your host Amelia. Today is Tuesday 16. Today's episode was curated by DeepSeek v3.2 Speciale.
The world is closer than ever to a peace deal to end the war in Ukraine – but the final stretch is proving to be a diplomatic minefield. Italian Foreign Minister Antonio Tajani declared today that the agreement is “90 percent complete,” thanks in large part to Donald Trump’s shuttle diplomacy. Yet within hours, Moscow laid down its red lines: no NATO troops on Ukrainian soil, and no concessions on the territories it has seized – meaning Donbass and the southern regions remain firmly in Russian hands. President Zelensky, for his part, insists that Ukraine will never recognize the Donbass as Russian. Meanwhile, behind the scenes, Europe’s big three – Italy, France, and Germany – are caught in a classic Catch‑22, each waiting for the other to shoulder the political burden of pressuring Kyiv into accepting painful compromises. The left‑wing press warns that caving to Putin would reward aggression, while the right celebrates a historic chance to stop the bloodshed. For now, the champagne remains on ice.
While diplomats wrangle over Ukraine, back in Brussels, the European Commission is preparing a major U‑turn on another front: the future of the internal combustion engine. After years of insisting that all new cars sold from 2035 must be zero‑emission, Brussels is now expected to propose a revision that would allow combustion engines to stay on the road – as long as they run on synthetic fuels or other low‑carbon technologies. The move comes after intense lobbying from Germany and Italy, home to Europe’s largest carmakers, who argued that an outright ban would cost jobs and ignore technological alternatives. Environmental groups are outraged, with left‑leaning papers like *La Repubblica* calling it a betrayal of the EU’s green transition. On the right, *Il Giornale* celebrates a return to sanity after what it calls “years of ideological diktats.”
Meanwhile, here at home, the Italian government is opening the spending taps for defense. Prime Minister Meloni’s cabinet has signed off on four urgent decrees that unlock 3.5 billion euros for the armed forces, with the money earmarked for drones, ships, and submarines. The move signals Rome’s commitment to bolstering its military capabilities at a time when Europe is rearming in the shadow of the Ukraine war and rising tensions in the Mediterranean. The left is already questioning the priorities – arguing that the funds would be better spent on healthcare or education – while the right counters that a strong defense is non‑negotiable in an increasingly dangerous world.
But before we go, here are a few other stories that caught our eye today. First, Italy’s inflation rate dropped to 1.1% in November, the lowest since January, thanks largely to falling energy prices – a rare bit of good news for households. Second, Rome’s city hall is set to introduce a 2‑euro ticket to visit the Trevi Fountain starting January 7th. The move could bring in an estimated 20 million euros per year, though critics call it a toll on culture. And finally, Australian police are investigating a trip the Sydney attackers made to the Philippines, suggesting international jihadist links. The death toll stands at 12, with many more wounded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-16</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-16/2025-12-16-audio.mp3" length="3794696" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>237</itunes:duration>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
