<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Italy Today</title>
    <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today</link>
    <description>Daily briefing on Italian news</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <image>
      <url>https://briefings.my/italy-today/cover.png</url>
      <title>Italy Today</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today</link>
    </image>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 18:43:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <itunes:image href="https://briefings.my/italy-today/cover.png"/>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-15</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-15/2025-12-15-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**THE ROMAN OBSERVER**
Buongiorno, I am Amelia. It is Monday 15, and here is the view from Rome. Today's briefing was curated by DeepSeek-V3.2-Special.
**PART 1: THE HEADLINES (The &quot;Terza Pagina&quot;)**
1. **The Imam's Release: Government vs Judiciary**  
   - **The Fact:** A Turin court ordered the release of Tunisian imam Mohamed Shahin from a detention center, ruling his continued detention unlawful.  
   - **The Spin:** While left-leaning La Repubblica reported the decision with a focus on the legal reasoning, right-wing Il Giornale echoed Premier Meloni's outrage, accusing the judiciary of undermining national security.  
   - **The Takeaway:** The case underscores the escalating conflict between the executive and the judiciary over immigration policy, with both sides digging in.
2. **Budget Ballooning: 3.5 Billion for Businesses, Bridge Funds Delayed**  
   - **The Fact:** The government unveiled a last-minute package of €3.5 billion in the budget law, earmarked for business support, while postponing funding for the controversial Messina Bridge project.  
   - **The Spin:** Opposition parties and left-wing media slammed the move as proof of disarray, while Economy Minister Giorgetti argued it was necessary to boost a faltering economy.  
   - **The Takeaway:** The extra spending risks widening the deficit, but the real story is the quiet shelving of a flagship infrastructure promise.
3. **John Elkann Forced to Stand Trial Over Agnelli Inheritance**  
   - **The Fact:** A Milan judge ordered the forced indictment of Fiat chairman John Elkann on fraud charges related to the inheritance of Marella Caracciolo, widow of Gianni Agnelli.  
   - **The Spin:** Center-left outlets portrayed the decision as justice catching up with the elite; right-leaning commentators called it judicial overreach and pointed to Elkann's defense labeling the ruling &quot;abnormal.&quot;  
   - **The Takeaway:** The trial will shine an uncomfortable spotlight on Italy's most powerful industrial dynasty and could have ripple effects across the corporate landscape.
**PART 2: IL CAFFÈ (Rapid Fire)**  
- **Cannabis Sector Wins:** The Council of State ruled that companies can sell CBD oil, ending a two-year legal battle and giving a boost to Italy's hemp industry.  
- **IMF’s Mixed Report:** The IMF praised Italy's fiscal discipline but warned the government to &quot;keep pedaling&quot; to sustain growth and reduce public debt.  
- **Poll Shift:** A new poll shows a dip for Fratelli d'Italia and a rise for the Democratic Party, narrowing the gap.  
- **Ukraine Summit:** At the Berlin meeting, European leaders backed a multinational force for Ukraine and urged President Zelensky to consult his people on peace terms; Meloni said she expects &quot;progress.&quot;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-15</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-15/2025-12-15-audio.mp3" length="3148113" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>196</itunes:duration>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-16</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-16/2025-12-16-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**ITALY TODAY**
Welcome, I am your host Amelia. Today is Tuesday 16. Today's episode was curated by DeepSeek v3.2 Speciale.
The world is closer than ever to a peace deal to end the war in Ukraine – but the final stretch is proving to be a diplomatic minefield. Italian Foreign Minister Antonio Tajani declared today that the agreement is “90 percent complete,” thanks in large part to Donald Trump’s shuttle diplomacy. Yet within hours, Moscow laid down its red lines: no NATO troops on Ukrainian soil, and no concessions on the territories it has seized – meaning Donbass and the southern regions remain firmly in Russian hands. President Zelensky, for his part, insists that Ukraine will never recognize the Donbass as Russian. Meanwhile, behind the scenes, Europe’s big three – Italy, France, and Germany – are caught in a classic Catch‑22, each waiting for the other to shoulder the political burden of pressuring Kyiv into accepting painful compromises. The left‑wing press warns that caving to Putin would reward aggression, while the right celebrates a historic chance to stop the bloodshed. For now, the champagne remains on ice.
While diplomats wrangle over Ukraine, back in Brussels, the European Commission is preparing a major U‑turn on another front: the future of the internal combustion engine. After years of insisting that all new cars sold from 2035 must be zero‑emission, Brussels is now expected to propose a revision that would allow combustion engines to stay on the road – as long as they run on synthetic fuels or other low‑carbon technologies. The move comes after intense lobbying from Germany and Italy, home to Europe’s largest carmakers, who argued that an outright ban would cost jobs and ignore technological alternatives. Environmental groups are outraged, with left‑leaning papers like *La Repubblica* calling it a betrayal of the EU’s green transition. On the right, *Il Giornale* celebrates a return to sanity after what it calls “years of ideological diktats.”
Meanwhile, here at home, the Italian government is opening the spending taps for defense. Prime Minister Meloni’s cabinet has signed off on four urgent decrees that unlock 3.5 billion euros for the armed forces, with the money earmarked for drones, ships, and submarines. The move signals Rome’s commitment to bolstering its military capabilities at a time when Europe is rearming in the shadow of the Ukraine war and rising tensions in the Mediterranean. The left is already questioning the priorities – arguing that the funds would be better spent on healthcare or education – while the right counters that a strong defense is non‑negotiable in an increasingly dangerous world.
But before we go, here are a few other stories that caught our eye today. First, Italy’s inflation rate dropped to 1.1% in November, the lowest since January, thanks largely to falling energy prices – a rare bit of good news for households. Second, Rome’s city hall is set to introduce a 2‑euro ticket to visit the Trevi Fountain starting January 7th. The move could bring in an estimated 20 million euros per year, though critics call it a toll on culture. And finally, Australian police are investigating a trip the Sydney attackers made to the Philippines, suggesting international jihadist links. The death toll stands at 12, with many more wounded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-16</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-16/2025-12-16-audio.mp3" length="3794696" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>237</itunes:duration>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-17</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-17/2025-12-17-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**ITALY TODAY**
Welcome, I am your host Amelia. Today is Wednesday 17. Today's episode was curated by DeepSeek v3.2 Speciale.
**SECTION 1: THE LEAD**
Italy's highest court has delivered the final word in the legal saga of Matteo Salvini and the Open Arms migrant rescue ship. The Cassazione definitively acquitted the former interior minister, confirming earlier rulings that he did not commit kidnapping or abuse of office when he blocked the vessel from docking in 2019. Salvini, now deputy prime minister, declared: &quot;Defending borders is not a crime.&quot; Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni immediately seized the moment, calling for applause in the Senate and hailing the verdict as a victory for the rule of law. As often in Italy, the news divided the press along familiar lines: *Il Giornale* celebrated the end of what it called &quot;the great Open Arms hoax,&quot; while *La Repubblica* focused on the political theatre, noting Meloni's demand for applause. The left-leaning *Fanpage* and *Il Fatto Quotidiano* warned that the ruling could embolden anti-immigrant policies, but with the Supreme Court’s decision, this six‑year legal battle is now closed.
**SECTION 2: THE ROUNDUP**
*Pension reform sparks coalition clash*
While the courtroom drama ends, a fierce battle is brewing over pensions. The government's budget law includes a double tightening: raising the retirement age and slashing the value of buying back contribution years for university graduates – the so‑called *riscatto della laurea*. *Il Sole 24 Ore*, the authoritative business daily, outlines the technical measures, which aim to contain Italy's ballooning pension costs. But the Lega, a junior partner in the coalition, has tabled an amendment to scrap the entire pension package, calling it unfair. Under pressure, Prime Minister Meloni has already admitted that the graduate‑year rule was poorly drafted and promised to correct it so that it applies only to future contributions. The left, meanwhile, condemns the reforms as an attack on workers, with *La Repubblica* quoting union leaders threatening protests. The coming days will test the unity of the governing majority.
*Ukraine: no troops from Italy, and a gloomy forecast*
Turning to foreign affairs, Prime Minister Meloni used a speech in Parliament to rule out any Italian military deployment to Ukraine. &quot;We will not send soldiers,&quot; she stated, adding that Moscow's demands remain &quot;unreasonable.&quot; Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky struck a pessimistic note, telling *La Repubblica* that &quot;signals from Moscow are clear – 2026 will be a year of war.&quot; In London, new Prime Minister Keir Starmer has issued an ultimatum to Russian oligarch Roman Abramovich: donate the 2.5 billion euros from the sale of Chelsea Football Club to Ukraine, or face legal action. The move is part of Western efforts to use frozen Russian assets for reconstruction. On the other side, Vladimir Putin insulted European leaders, calling them &quot;pigs&quot; and &quot;profiteers,&quot; and vowed to win on the battlefield. As peace talks continue behind the scenes, the public rhetoric suggests the conflict is far from over.
**SECTION 3: THE WRAP-UP**
But before we go, here are a few other stories making headlines. First, Italy's spread – the gap between Italian and German 10‑year bond yields – has fallen to 66 basis points, its lowest level since 2009, signaling strong investor confidence. Second, the government has unveiled a major reform of condominium rules: administrators will need a university degree, cash payments are banned, and all owners can be held liable for unpaid fees. And finally, in the ongoing saga of the &quot;family in the woods,&quot; social services reported that the children are afraid of showers and struggle with hygiene, while the family's lawyer insists they can read and write, contradicting earlier claims.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-17</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-17/2025-12-17-audio.mp3" length="4544515" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>284</itunes:duration>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-18</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-18/2025-12-18-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**ITALY TODAY**
Welcome, I am your host Amelia. Today is Thursday, December 18. Today's episode was curated by Gemini 3 Pro.
**SECTION 1: THE LEAD**
In Turin, the thirty-year experiment of &quot;illegal but tolerated&quot; is officially over. At dawn this morning, police forces initiated the eviction of Askatasuna, the city’s most notorious social center, a stronghold of the antagonism that has defined Turin’s radical left since the 1990s. The operation quickly turned the streets into a battlefield. *Corriere della Sera* reports a chaotic scene of firecrackers and stones launched by activists, met instantly by police water cannons.
The reaction from the press tells you exactly where the fault lines lie. *La Stampa*—the historic voice of Turin’s industrial establishment, whose offices were actually targeted by these same groups earlier this year—frames the eviction as a necessary restoration of order and a &quot;defense of democracy&quot; endorsed by the center-left Mayor Stefano Lo Russo. Conversely, the right-wing *Libero Quotidiano* and *Il Giornale* are practically cheering, describing the subsequent protests not as activism but as &quot;guerrilla warfare&quot; and citing the eviction as proof that the government is finally dismantling the &quot;zones of impunity&quot; tolerated by previous administrations. Meanwhile, *Fanpage* focuses on the ground level, reporting on the anger of students and the aggressive police tactics, including a disturbing report of a 15-year-old allegedly forced to strip during a street search. For three decades, Askatasuna was a political headache; today, it is a police record.
**SECTION 2: THE ROUNDUP**
**Following up on yesterday’s report regarding the pension battle:** the government has blinked. Yesterday, we told you about the fierce coalition infighting over a proposal to hike the costs for university graduates buying back their study years for pension credits—the famous *riscatto della laurea*. Today, *Il Sole 24 Ore* confirms the retreat: Economy Minister Giancarlo Giorgetti has reformulated the amendment. The proposed tightening will no longer be retroactive, meaning &quot;acquired rights&quot; are safe, and the cost increase is effectively off the table for now. It was a classic Roman trial balloon: floated in the committee, popped by public outcry, and now quietly swept away to keep the coalition peace.
**Meanwhile, buried deep within that same budget law,** a far quieter but potentially more significant change is taking shape. *La Repubblica* sounds the alarm on what it calls a government &quot;blitz&quot; to deregulate the arms industry. A new amendment reportedly simplifies the authorization process for the production and export of weaponry, removing certain checks and balances. While the opposition frames this as a dangerous shift toward a war economy, *Il Sole 24 Ore* analyzes it through a purely industrial lens, noting that the move is designed to align Italian defense manufacturing with the surging European demand for armaments. In Italy, even the business of war is ultimately a debate about bureaucracy.
**SECTION 3: THE WRAP-UP**
But before we go, here are a few other stories making the rounds.
First, the European Central Bank has decided to keep interest rates steady at 2%. *Corriere della Sera* notes that while inflation is under control, the bank is still cautious about declaring 'mission accomplished.'
Also, the Ministry of Tourism is back in the spotlight. After the digital &quot;Open to Meraviglia&quot; influencer campaign was mocked for using AI, Minister Daniela Santanchè has launched a &quot;flesh and bone&quot; Venus to represent Italy. *Il Fatto Quotidiano* is naturally merciless, mocking the casting call for a &quot;sexy&quot; tourist icon.
And finally, the investigation into &quot;hiring friends and family&quot; for the Milan-Cortina Olympics seems to be winding down. Prosecutors have asked to archive the case involving the son of Senate President Ignazio La Russa, proving once again that in Italy, nepotism is often considered bad taste, but rarely a crime.
That is the state of the country today. I will see you tomorrow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-18</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-18/2025-12-18-audio.mp3" length="4814934" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>300</itunes:duration>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Italy Today - 2025-12-19</title>
      <link>https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-19/2025-12-19-audio.mp3</link>
      <description>**ITALY TODAY**
Welcome, I am your host Amelia. Today is Friday, December 19. Today's episode was curated by Gemini 3 Pro.
**SECTION 1: THE LEAD**
Following up on yesterday's report, the cracks in the government coalition we mentioned have turned into a landslide. If yesterday was about a tactical retreat on university pension buybacks, today is about a strategic surrender on the entire pension front. During a chaotic night in the Budget Committee, the government majority effectively deleted its own proposals to reform the pension system for 2026.
According to *Il Sole 24 Ore*—the sober voice of the business community—a full-blown government crisis was &quot;avoided by a whisper.&quot; To keep the peace between the League and Forza Italia, the executive scrapped the controversial changes to the &quot;TFR&quot; severance pay and the tightening of early retirement rules. Effectively, the government has chosen stability over reform, opting to leave things exactly as they are rather than risk a vote that could shatter the alliance.
The reaction this morning is a perfect study in Italian media spin. *La Repubblica* and the Democratic Party are claiming victory, with opposition leader Elly Schlein declaring that &quot;the majority is broken&quot; and arguing that the government is paralyzed by infighting. Conversely, the right-wing papers are looking elsewhere. *Libero Quotidiano* and *Il Giornale* completely ignore the pension failure, focusing instead on the one victory the coalition managed to secure: a new 1,500 euro &quot;voucher&quot; for families sending children to private, parochial schools. For the Right, this is a triumph for educational freedom; for the rest of the country, it looks like a consolation prize in a budget law that has largely decided to do nothing at all.
**SECTION 2: THE ROUNDUP**
Moving from the paralysis in Parliament to the cold case that never sleeps...
There has been a significant, albeit mysterious, development in the disappearance of Emanuela Orlandi—the Vatican citizen who vanished into thin air 42 years ago. *Corriere della Sera* and *Adnkronos* report that the Rome Prosecutor’s office has formally placed a new person under investigation. While the suspect’s name remains shielded, the charge is &quot;false information to a public prosecutor.&quot; This suggests investigators believe someone is still lying to protect the secrets of 1983. While *La Stampa* highlights this as a &quot;colpo di scena&quot;—a plot twist—veteran observers remain skeptical. In Italy, new investigations into Orlandi usually signal the beginning of a new mystery, rather than the end of the old one.
Meanwhile, prepare your wallets if you are planning a trip to the capital. After months of speculation, it is official: looking at the Trevi Fountain will complicate your logistics, and eventually, your bank account. *AGI* and *Il Post* report that starting February 1st, access to the fountain’s lower basin will be restricted and ticketed at two euros. Mayor Roberto Gualtieri argues this is about crowd control rather than revenue, a view supported by *Il Messaggero’s* local reporting. However, critics fear this is the turning point where Rome ceases to be a city and officially becomes a theme park.
**SECTION 3: THE WRAP-UP**
But before we go, here are a few other stories making the rounds:
First, a major shakeup in the Italian media landscape. *La Repubblica* reports that the Del Vecchio family—heirs to the Luxottica eyewear fortune—has acquired a 30% stake in *Il Giornale*. It is a fascinating move: a family historically aligned with liberal finance buying into the house organ of the institutional Right.
Also, Italian fashion continues its eastward migration. *Corriere della Sera* notes that the luxury sneaker brand &quot;Golden Goose&quot; has been sold to a consortium including funds from Hong Kong and Singapore for 2.5 billion euros.
And finally, tensions are spiking in the Mediterranean. *La Verità* and *Repubblica* both report that a Russian oil tanker was struck, allegedly by Ukraine, in waters surprisingly close to Sicily. The war, it seems, is no longer just in the Black Sea.
That is the state of the country today. I will see you on Monday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-19</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://briefings.my/italy-today/artifacts/2025-12-19/2025-12-19-audio.mp3" length="5023496" type="audio/mpeg"/>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <itunes:duration>313</itunes:duration>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
